Guide to the Dial/Scofield Thayer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Many of the Harvard verses carry the comments of Thayer's writing tutor Hermann Hagedorn, who criticized his "dismally artificial verses" and "pretentious sonnets" freely. At one point he cited an unfavorable review of his own poetry by Santayana as encouragement to Thayer "to learn it with me." The submissions to the Harvard Monthly are also filled with editors' (mostly unfavorable) comments, including some signed "GVS" for Gilbert Vivian Seldes.
Thayer's mature poetry is found in folders 1760-1821. About twenty of the individual poems were published by the Dial following Thayer's resignation in 1925. Others were set up for the Dial but never actually published. Many were published unsigned. Thayer submitted several poems, including "Leo Arrogans," under pseudonyms at various times; most of these were rejected by the editors. Several poems have autobiographical interest, including "To the Acting Editor of the Dial ," the unpublished "To One Who was Betrayed," and "To Fritz Klatt." For example, "On an Old Painting of Portsmouth Harbor...," describes the difficulties and confusions faced by an expatriate: "There is no sense in buying pictures And swimming them across the sea; The sun and moon have laid old strictures On what a continent shall be."
Most of Thayer's preserved prose was written for the Dial, and is located in Series III, Boxes 25-26, folders 620-58. Manuscripts found in Series V includes several versions of his 1926 "Berlin Letter" and a draft of his Dial comment on the McAlmon-Ellermann marriage. Folder 1829 contains the first, long version of Thayer's 1925 letter "To the Editors of The Dial ," which goes on to accuse Burke, Watson, and several members of the staff of entering into an unspecified conspiracy against Thayer.
"Writings of Others" contains a corrected, signed typescript of John Jay Chapman's "The Treason and Death of Benedict Arnold," poems by Thayer's Oxford friend Robert Parr, and galleys of Marianne Moore's first collected edition of poems, extensively annotated by Thayer.
Other material of interest in Series V includes several folders of playbills from Austrian and German theaters in the 1920s, newspaper clippings collected by Thayer on such topics as the Fatty Arbuckle case and the suitability of Mother Goose for children's reading, and four folders of inventories of books owned by Thayer.
Series VI, Artwork, is housed in Boxes 69-73 and contains papers documenting Thayer's extensive art collection as well as illustration blocks and drawings by Cummings and Dehn. "Bills and receipts" fill folders 1856-82. These document Thayer's purchases and have been filed as he filed them, alphabetically by dealer's name. While many of these are for prints and etchings, there are also receipts concerning, for example, his purchases of an Assumption of the Virgin by Rubens from Kunstverlag Wulfrum, a Bonnard from the Independent Gallery, and lithographs by Degas, Munch, and Schiele from Max Hevesi.
Further information on Thayer's extensive holdings and acquisitions can be found in folders 1887-93, whose contents include a precise customs declaration filed by Thayer in Austria in 1922 listing works of art, with the date, place and price of purchase, and lists of the contents of his apartment at 80 Washington Square.
Thayer's ambitious Living Art project included both the publication of the lavish folio and a traveling exhibition of these and other modern works. Folder 1897 contains correspondence in which Thayer offered the exhibit to several museums and galleries, nearly all of which refused it. Information on the folio itself includes Thayer's drafts, a publication announcement, and newspaper clippings of reviews, many favorable. There are several versions of the introduction to the folio, which Thayer hoped would contribute to "a richer and more sound national and artistic life," as well as serving "to sharpen our tastes and to heighten our pleasures." These drafts, located in folders 1898-1906, contain perhaps the fullest statement available of Thayer's aesthetic theories.
In the course of his travels and purchases, Thayer gathered illustrations of artworks from many sources, including dealer's catalogs, magazines, and newspapers. Some of these are found in Box 70, folder 1913-33.
Boxes 71-73 hold blocks on which plates for full-color reproductions are mounted, most of works by modern painters, including Picasso, Matisse, and Manet. It is uncertain whether these were intended for use in the Dial.
Oversize material has been placed at the end of the collection in series order. Contents include a 1924 accountant's report for Dial Press, an annotated copy of Pound's "Fourth Canto," a handbill advertising a general strike of the Paper Box Makers Union in 1919, the 1916 want ads from a Chicago newspaper that Thayer used while at the YMCA, and drawings by E. E. Cummings and Adolf Dehn.
Series VII, Formerly Restricted Papers, were restricted until May 24, 2012 under the terms of the sale agreement. Contents include over three boxes of letters from Scofield Thayer to Elaine Orr, dating from 1912 through 1925; an undated E. E. Cummings letter to Thayer; and many notepads recording personal thoughts, similar to those in Box 53.
Restricted Fragile Papers are housed in Box 83.
Adultery; Aesthetics, Modern -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; American periodicals; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art -- Private collections; Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Authors and patrons; Authors and publishers; Divorce; European literature -- 20th Century; Free love -- United States; Little magazines; Modernism (Art); Modernism (Literature); Mothers and sons; Periodicals -- Publishing -- Finance; Publishers and publishing; World War, 1914-1918; Austria -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; Europe -- Description and travel; United States -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Barnes, Albert C. (Albert Coombs), 1872-1951; Bodenheim, Maxwell, 1893-1954; Bourne, Randolph Silliman, 1886-1918; Bryant, Louise, 1885-1936; Burke, Kenneth, 1897-1993; Craig, Samuel W.; Crane, Hart, 1899-1932; Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1894-1962; Dehn, Adolf, 1895-1968; Demuth, Charles, 1883-1935; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Eliot, Vivienne, 1888-1947; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939; Gregory, Alyse, 1884-1967; Johnson, Martyn; Joyce, James, 1882-1941; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; McBride, Henry, 1867-1962; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Mortimer, Raymond, 1895-1980; Nichols, Robert, 1893-1944; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963; Powys, Llewelyn, 1884-1939; Saintsbury, George, 1845-1933; Santayana, George, 1863-1952; Seldes, Gilbert, 1893-1970; Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955; Thayer, Scofield, 1889-1982; Watson, James S. (James Sibley), 1894-1982; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Wright, Cuthbert; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939; Bancroft School; Dial Magazine; Harvard University -- Class of 1913
- Office Correspondence, 1922-29; Series I; 3.5; (8 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Office Correspondence, is housed in Boxes
  1-8 and contains alphabetically arranged correspondence.
  All letters have been placed in chronological order
  within each folder. Note: This series contains
  correspondence with employees of the Dial. For
  correspondence with Scofield Thayer, see Series IV.
  - Aiken, Conrad, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Aldington, Richard, 1924-27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anderson, Sherwood, 1924-26, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Archipenko, Alexandre, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arensburg, Walter, 1926
  - "B" general, 1927-28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Balazs, Bella, 1924-25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beach, Sylvia, 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bell, Clive, 1924-25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bell, Lisle, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
  - Bodenheim, Maxwell, 1924-26 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Bosschère, Jean de, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bragdon, Claude, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1924-25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Budberg, Marie, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 25-29)
  - Butts, Mary, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bynner, Witter, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "C" general, 1924-28 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Campbell, Joseph, 1925-26 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Claudel, Paul, 1928
  - Coatsworth, Elizabeth J., 1924-27 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Colum, Padraic, 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 36-39)
  - Coomaraswamy, Ananda K., 1926-27 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Coppard, A. E., 1924-27
  - Corkery, Daniel, 1926-29 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Cournos, John, 1926-29
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1924-28 (Box 2, Folder 42-46)
  - Craig, Gordon, 1926-28 (Box 2, Folder 47-48)
  - Crane, Hart, 1923-28 (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
  - Craven, Thomas, 1924-28 (Box 2, Folder 51-54)
  - Cummings, E. E., 1924-27, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "D" general, 1927-29 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Damon, S. Foster, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Dehn, Adolf, 1926-28 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - De la Mare, Walter, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Demuth, Charles, n.d.
  - Dillon, George, 1924-28 (Box 2, Folder 60-61)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1923-24, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Eliot, T. S., 1920-29 (Box 2, Folder 63-65)
  - Ellis, Havelock, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Erdberg, Amy von, 1923-28 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Erdberg, Monica von, 1928
  - Erdberg, Robert von, 1922-27 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Faggi, Alfeo, 1924-29 (Box 2, Folder 69-70)
  - Faure, Elie, 1923-25, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Fowler, H. W., 1926
  - Frank, Waldo, 1926-28 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Frost, Robert, 1924
  - Fry, Roger, 1924-27 (Box 2, Folder 74-75)
  - "G" general, 1925, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Galantière, Lewis, 1926-27 (Box 2, Folder 77-78)
  - Garnett, David, 1923-24 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Gilman, Lawrence, 1924-27
  - Gould, Joseph, 1926-28 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Gregory, Alyse, 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 81-89)
  - Gropper, William V., 1924-27, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Hande, Louise, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Hardy, Thomas, 1924
  - Hartman, Bertram, 1925-28 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Hemingway, Ernest, 1924-25
  - Hillyer, Robert, 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 93-95)
  - Hofmannsthal, Hugo von, 1924-29, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Johnson, Richard V., 1926 (Box 3, Folder 96a)
  - Joyce, James, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - "K" general, 1926-28 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Kent, Rockwell
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Craven, Thomas, Box 30, folder 781
  - Kreymborg, Alfred, 1924-27 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Kubin, Alfred, 1928
  - "L" general, 1924-26 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Lachaise, Gaston, 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Lankes, Julius J., 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 102-03)
  - Larsson, R. Ellsworth, 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 104-06)
  - Lawrence, D. H., 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Leach, Henry Goddard, 1926-29 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Lewis, Wyndham, 1925
  - Linati, Carlo, n.d.
  - Littell, Philip, 1925-28 (Box 3, Folder 109-10)
  - Lochner, Louis, 1924-29 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Lovett, Robert Morse, 1924-26 (Box 3, Folder 112-13)
  - Loving, Pierre, 1926-29 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - McBride, Henry, 1924-27 (Box 3, Folder 115-20)
  - McBride, Henry, 1928-29 (Box 4, Folder 121-22)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1925-28 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Magee, W. K., 1924-29 (Box 4, Folder 124-29)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1924-29 (Box 4, Folder 130-31)
  - Mencken, H. L., 1924, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Miller, Kenneth, 1927
  - Mitchell, Stewart, 1925-28 (Box 4, Folder 133-34)
  - Monro, Harold, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Moore, George, 1923-27
  - Moore, Marianne, 1924-27, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 136-42)
  - Morand, Raymond, 1924-28 (Box 4, Folder 143-47)
  - Mortimer, Raymond, 1924-29 (Box 4, Folder 148-49)
  - Muir, Edwin, 1924-25 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Murry, J. Middleton, 1924, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Noguchi, Yorie, 1928-29 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - "O" general, 1924-29 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Ortega y Gasset, José, 1924-25 (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - Ortega y Gasset, M., 1925-27 (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Pankhurst, Sylvia, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Piccoli, Rafaello, 1924-29 (Box 4, Folder 157-58)
  - Poore, Dudley, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Pound, Ezra, 1925-29 (Box 5, Folder 160-65)
  - Powys, John Cooper, 1924-29 (Box 5, Folder 166-69)
  - Powys, Llewellyn, 1924-29 (Box 5, Folder 170-71)
  - Powys, Theodore F., 1924-27 (Box 5, Folder 172)
  - "R" general, 1924-27 (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - Richards, I. A., 1926 (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Ridge, Lola, 1924-29 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Robinson, Boardman, 1922-24 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1922-24 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Robinson, James Harvey, 1922-23 (Box 5, Folder 178)
  - Robinson, Lennox, 1929
  - Rönnebeck, Arnold, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - Rosenfeld, Paul, 1922-29 (Box 5, Folder 180-85)
  - Ruiz, José Martinez, 1926-28 (Box 5, Folder 186)
  - Russell, Bertrand, 1922-29, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 187-91)
  - "S" general, 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 192)
  - Saintsbury, George, 1922-27 (Box 5, Folder 193-97)
  - Saintsbury, George, 1927-29 (Box 6, Folder 198-200)
  - Sandburg, Carl, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 201)
  - Santayana, George, 1923-27 (Box 6, Folder 202-03)
  - Sassoon, Siegfried, 1924-25 (Box 6, Folder 204)
  - Scheffauer, Herman George, 1924-26
  - Schloezer, Boris de, 1928-29 (Box 6, Folder 205)
  - Schnitzler, Arthur, 1922-24
  - Scott, Evelyn, 1925-28 (Box 6, Folder 206)
  - Seldes, Gilbert, 1920-29 (Box 6, Folder 207-226)
  - Seligman, Herbert, 1924-25 (Box 6, Folder 227)
  - Sherman, Stuart P., 1922
  - Sitwell, Sacheverell, 1923, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 228)
  - Smith, Logan Pearsall, 1922-29 (Box 6, Folder 229-30)
  - Soupault, Philippe, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 231)
  - Spingarn, J. E., 1922-24
  - Sprinchorn, Carl, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 232)
  - Stein, Gertrude, 1923-28 (Box 6, Folder 233)
  - Stein, Leo, 1927-28 (Box 6, Folder 234)
  - Stephens, James, 1922-25 (Box 6, Folder 235)
  - Stevens, Wallace, 1922-27 (Box 7, Folder 236-37)
  - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1921-26 (Box 7, Folder 238-39)
  - Strand, Paul, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 240)
  - Strong, L. A. G., 1924-29 (Box 7, Folder 241-42)
  - Toomer, Jean, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 243)
  - Trites, W. B., n.d.
  - Trueblood, Charles K., 1922-29 (Box 7, Folder 244-52)
  - Unamuno, Miguel de, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 253)
  - Valéry, Paul, 1925-29 (Box 7, Folder 254)
  - Van Doren, Carl, 1922-23 (Box 7, Folder 255)
  - Van Loon, Hendrick Willem, 1922-24, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 256)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 257)
  - "W" general, 1924-29, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 258)
  - Walkowitz, A., 1928 (Box 7, Folder 259)
  - Watson, J. S., 1922-29 (Box 7, Folder 260-74)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1922-27 (Box 7, Folder 275-78)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 279)
  - Willett, B. W., 1925
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1922-29 (Box 8, Folder 280-87)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1922-25, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 288-89)
  - Winton, Eugene, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 290)
  - Woolf, Virginia, 1923-24
  - Wright, Cuthbert, 1924-28, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 291-95)
  - Wright, Willard Huntington, 1922-23 (Box 8, Folder 296)
  - Wrynn, Anthony, 1924-28 (Box 8, Folder 297)
  - Wylie, Elinor, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 298)
  - Yeats, Jack B., 1923-26
  - Yeats, William Butler, 1922-28, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 299-300)
  - Zweig, Stefan, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 301)
- Dial Office Files, 1918-29; Series II; 7.5; (10 boxes)
  - Advertising and Promotion
    - Advertisements, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 302)
    - Circular lists, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 303)
    - Clip sheets
      See: Oversize, Box 74, folder 1937
    - Index to Volume LXIX (Box 9, Folder 304)
    - Letter to subscribers, 1920
    - Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 305)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 306)
    - Posters
      See: Oversize, Box 74, folder 1938
    - Samples of advertisements, 1922-24 (Box 9, Folder 307-08)
    - Statements of purpose, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 309-11)
    - Style book, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 312)
  - Editorial Files
    - American Mercury files, 1924-25 (Box 9, Folder 313)
    - "Americana" files, 1924-25, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 314-15)
      See also: Oversize, Box 74, folders 1939-40
    - "Comment" files, 1921-24, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 316)
    - Copyright memorandum (Box 9, Folder 317)
    - General Instructions, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 318-19)
      See also: Oversize, Box 74, folder 1941
    - Lists of accepted material, 1922-23 (Box 9, Folder 320-21)
      See also: Box 40, folders 1123-51
    - Miscellaneous lists, 1925-26, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 322-23)
    - Miscellaneous reviews and clippings, 1922, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 324)
  - Financial Papers
    - Certificate of incorporation, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 325)
    - Contracts for Dial Press, 1923-24 (Box 9, Folder 326)
    - Financial reports, 1920-25 (Box 9, Folder 327-32)
      See also: Oversize, Box 74, folder 1942
  - Oversize
    - Card files
      - Book review file, [1921-24] (Box 10, Folder 333)
      - Submissions file, [1924-29?] (Box 11a, Folder 334a)
      - Submissions file, [1924-29?] (Box 11b, Folder 334b)
      - Submissions file, [1924-29?] (Box 11c, Folder 334c)
      - Submissions file, [1924-29?] (Box 11d, Folder 334d)
      - Submissions file, [1924-29?] (Box 11e, Folder 334e)
      - Submissions file, [1924-29?] (Box 11f, Folder 334f)
    - Scrapbooks
      Advertisements
      - "Appreciations", 1920 (Box 12, Folder 335)
      - "Circulars and Circular Letters", 1920-24, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 336)
      - "House Ads", 1920-26 (Box 13, Folder 337)
      - "House Ads", 1926-29 (Box 13, Folder 338)
      - "Paid and Exchange Ads", 1920-22 (Box 14, Folder 339)
      - "Paid and Exchange Ads", 1922-25 (Box 14, Folder 340)
      - "Paid and Exchange Ads", 1925-29 (Box 15, Folder 341)
      - "Testimonials", 1920-22, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 342)
      - Newspaper clippings
        - "Clippings I", 1920-23 (Box 16, Folder 343)
        - "Clippings II", 1922-24 (Box 16, Folder 344)
        - "Clippings III", 1924-25 (Box 17, Folder 345)
        - "Clippings IV", 1925-28 (Box 17, Folder 346)
        - "Clippings V", 1928-29 (Box 18, Folder 347)
    - Sample style book, 1921-28 (Box 18, Folder 347a)
- Dial Manuscripts, 1918-28; Series III; 3.75; (9 boxes)
  Series III, Dial Manuscripts, is arranged
  alphabetically by author and then by title. In the case
  of authors represented by more than ten titles, the
  material has been arranged alphabetically by genre and
  then by title within each genre. All material is either
  typescript and/or galley proof unless otherwise noted.
  - Æ: Poem Arlen, Michael: "The Ci-Devant", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 348)
  - Anderson, Sherwood
    - "I am a Fool", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 349)
    - "In Prison", n.d.
    - "The Man's Story", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 350)
    - "A Meeting South", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 351)
    - "The New Englander" (Box 19, Folder 352)
    - "Out of Nowhere into Nothing", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 353)
    - "The Triumph of the Egg", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 354)
  - Aragon, Louis: "Madame a sa tour monte" Balazs, Bela: "Ungärisher Brief", 1923 Apr (Box 19, Folder 355)
  - Barnes, Djuna: "First Communion", n.d.
  - Bell, Clive: "Virginia Woolf", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 356)
  - Birrell, Francis: "Marcel Proust", 1923 May (Box 19, Folder 357)
  - Bourne, Randolph: "An Autobiographical Chapter", 1920 Jan (Box 19, Folder 358)
  - Bragdon, Claude: "A Footnote on Æ", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 359)
  - Britten, Clarence: "Utopia Revisited", n.d.
  - Brooks, Van Wyck
    - "Henry James" (3 parts), n.d. (Box 19, Folder 360)
    - The Ordeal of Mark Twain: excerpts, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 361)
  - Burke, Kenneth
    - "The Consequences of Idealism", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 362)
    - "The Correspondence of Flaubert"
    - "The Critics of Dostoevsky", n.d.
    - "Declamations"
      - "A Declamation", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 363)
      - "Second Declamation"
      - "Third Declamation", n.d.
      - "Fourth Declamation", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 364)
      - "Fifth Declamation", n.d.
      - "Sixth Declamation", n.d.
    - "From Outside", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 365)
    - "Heaven's First Law", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 366)
    - "Mrs. Macenas", 1920 Feb
    - ["Notes on Oswald Spengler"], n.d. (Box 19, Folder 367)
    - "Portrait of an Arrived Critic", n.d.
    - "Psychology and Form"
  - Butts, Mary: "Change", 1922 (Box 19, Folder 368)
  - Campbell, Joseph: "Angel Flann and Devil Flann" (Box 19, Folder 369)
  - Coatsworth, Elizabeth: "Majesty Walks in the Garden", n.d.
  - Cohen-Portheim, Paul: "Thomas Mann," Autograph ms., n.d. (Box 19, Folder 370)
  - Craig, Gordon: "On Signora Eleonora Duse" (Box 19, Folder 371)
  - Crapsey, Adelaide: "Blue Hyacinths", 1922 (Box 19, Folder 372)
  - Cummings, E. E.
    Articles
    - "Gaston Lachaise", 1920 Feb (Box 19, Folder 373)
    - "The Theatre", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 374)
    - "T. S. Eliot", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 375)
    - Poetry
      - Five Poems: "into the strenuous briefness" "O sweet spontaneous" "but the other" "in Just-" "spring omnipotent goddess Thou", 1920 May (Box 19, Folder 376)
      - Five Poems: "of evident invisibles" "conversation with my friend is particularly" "it is at moments after which I have dreamed" "by little accurate traits saints have thickly which tread" "who's most afraid of death? thou" (Box 19, Folder 377)
      - Four Poems: "if being morticed with a dream" "i go to this window" "how this uncouth enchanted" "but if i should say" (Box 19, Folder 378)
      - Him, 1927, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 379-80)
      - Poem
      - "Nobody wears a yellow", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 381)
      - "Always before your voice my soul", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 382)
      - "supposing that i dreamed this", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 383)
      - Puella mea, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 384)
      - Seven Poems: "little tree" "the bigness of cannon" "when god lets my body be" "Buffalo Bill's" "why did you go" "when life is quite through with" "O Distinct", 1920 Jan (Box 19, Folder 385)
      - Seven Poems: "Suppose" "at dusk" "before the fragile gradual throne of night" "Take for example this" "of this sunset (which is so" "Paris; this April sunset completely utters" "will out of the kindness of their hearts a few philosophers tell us", 1923 Dec (Box 19, Folder 386)
      - "Eight sonnets, sixteen other things (none submitted to other magazines)" "lady you have written me a letter" "lady will you come with me into" "after all white horses are in bed" "like most godhouses this particular house" "sometimes i am alive because with" "o my wholly unwise and delicate" "the comedian stands on a corner, the sky is" "the, I should say, twenty-three year" "This is the vase, Here" "my humorous ghost precisely will" "being in love not with" "as one who(having written" "is" "Above a between-the-acts prattling of" "dawn" "but turning a corner" "Lady, i will touch you with my mind" "in front of your house i" "you said Is" (three versions) "when time deliberately is sponging sum after" "my smallheaded pearshaped mistress" "my youthful lady will have other lovers" "The Queen's" "somebody knew Lincoln somebody Xerxes" (Box 20, Folder 387)
      - Tulips and Chimneys
      - (1920 version) Cadences (Box 20, Folder 388)
      - (1920 version) "Epithalamion" (Box 20, Folder 389)
      - 1920 typescript (Box 20, Folder 390-95)
  - [DePollier, Dorothy]: "Briefer Mention", n.d. (Box 20, Folder 396)
  - Dewey, John: "Americanism and Localism", 1920 June (Box 20, Folder 397)
  - "China and the West", [1923 Feb]
  - Divoire, Fernand: "Case: Mallarmé," trans. by Ezra Pound (Box 20, Folder 398)
  - Eliot, T. S.
    - "An Emotional Unity", [1927] (Box 20, Folder 399)
    - "Isolated Superiority", n.d. (Box 20, Folder 400)
    - "London Letters," typescript and autograph ms., 1921-22 Aug,Nov (Box 20, Folder 401-03)